Register of the Karl Boromäus Frank papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Karl Boromäus Frank papers
1937-1961
71044
Hoover Institution Archives
10 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (4.0 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, clippings, printed matter, and photographs relating to the communist, socialist, and anti-Nazi movements in Germany, post-World War II reconstruction in Germany, and political psychology. Also available on microfilm (7 reels).
Frank, Karl Boromäus, 1893-1969.
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1971.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (7 reels).
Biographical Note
1893 May 31 Born, Vienna, Austria
1918 Received Ph.D. in Philosophy from the University of Vienna; thesis, "Contributions to the Psychology of the Lie" Author, Ueber Volks - und Rassenaberglauben (The Bias of Those Who Believe in National and Racial Prejudices and Superstition), Vienna & Leipzig, Suschitzky
1919 Joined the Austrian communist party
1920 Joined the German communist party
1923 Became a member of the right-wing of the communist party
1929 Left the communist party
1932 Joined the Social Democratic Party and Sozialistische Arbeiterpartei Deutschlands
1937 Married Anna Caples
1942 Author, Will Germany Crack?, Harper
1944 Author, Germany After Hitler, Farrar Rinehart
1946 Author, Erobert, Nicht Befreit; das Deutsche Volk im Ersten Jahre der Okkupation, Research Bureau, American Association for a Democratic Germany
1961 Died, New York City, New York
Karl Boromäus Frank, a German psychologist, socialist, anti-Nazi leader, author, and lecturer, was also known by the pseudonyms Paul Hagen, Wilhelm (Willi) Mueller, and Maria.
During his life, Frank was associated with a discussion group, sometimes called the "Miles Group" (Miles is a pseudonym for Walter Loewenheim); a representative of the "Neu Beginnen" group in various countries (Austria, Czechoslovakia, France, England); sometime Director of the New York branch of the "Overseas Branch" of the O.W.I.; and he participated in founding "American Friends of German Freedom" (was Director of Research, and Reinhold Niebuhr was Chairman) and the "Council for a Democratic Germany." Frank visited the United States on fundraising ventures in 1936-1936, and again in 1937, 1938 and 1939. He spent the last two decades of his life as a practicing psychologist in New York.
Scope and Content of Collection
Writings, correspondence, clippings, printed matter, and photographs relating to the communist, socialist, and anti-Nazi movements in Germany, post-World War II reconstruction in Germany, and political psychology. Also available on microfilm (7 reels).
American Friends of German Freedom.; Council for a Democratic Germany.; Kommunistishce Partei Deutschlands.; Neu Beginnen (Movement); Sozialistische Arbeiterpartei Deutschlands.; Sozialdemokratische Partei Deutschlands.; Anti-Nazi movement.; Communism--Germany.; National socialism.; Psychology.; Reconstruction (1939-1951)--Germany.; Socialism--Germany.
- ARTICLES, BOOK MANUSCRIPTS, AND OTHER WRITINGS
  - Articles, book manuscripts, and other writings, arranged chronologically, 1939-1945 (Box 1)
  - "What Not to Do with Germany; a Critical Review of Our Present Peace Plans" (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Germany After Hitler (1944), Farrar & Rinehart, manuscript (also comments and reviews) (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Will Germany Crack? (1942), Harper (comments and reviews) (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Clippings for proposed studies (Box-folder 2: 4-7)
    - "Psychoanalytical Interpretation of History"
    - "The Archaic: 1. West; 2. East"
    - "German Psychology"
  - Published articles (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Reviews (Box-folder 2: 9)
- LECTURES AND SPEECHES
  - Speakers' engagements, 1939-1942 (Box-folder 3: 1-3)
  - Lectures, 1943 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Lectures, 1944 (Box-folder 3: 5-6)
  - Lectures, 1945 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Newspaper clippings on lecture subjects (Dorothy Thompson, etc.), 1945-1946 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Speeches, 1944 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Lectures on "Political Irrationality,", 1958-1960 (Box-folder 4: 4)
- SUBJECT FILE
  - Formation of the Council for a Democratic Germany (letters of or to Thomas Mann, Louis Lochner, etc.) (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Society for the Prevention of World War III, Inc., New York (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Rex Stout Group (Box-folder 5: 3-4)
    Scope and Contents note
    Rex Stout was President of the Society for the Prevention of World War III.
  - "Neu Beginnen" (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Writers' War Board (Chairman: Rex Stout) (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Voice of Freedom, v. 1, no. 1 - no. 8, 1941 September - 1942 July/August (Box-folder 5: 7)
    Monthly bulletin of the International Co-ordination Council; Frank was instrumental in organizing this council.
  - Germany (American Association for a Democratic Germany) (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Post-war Germany (Box-folder 6: 2)
    Pamphlets, reprints, SIB Sozialdemokratischer Informations Brief, published by the Auslandsbüro "Neu Beginnen," 1939.
  - Selected credentials, etc. (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Autobiographical notes and projects presented to the OSS (Office of Strategic Services) (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Department of Justice. Foreign Agents Registration Section (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - The trip to Germany ("which never came off") (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Passport (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Visa question and Congressional action (re lecture trip to Canada) (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Immigration and Naturalization Service (regarding trip to Europe) (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Attacks on Karl Frank
    - Attacks against Hagen in the Press (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - Güunther Reinhardt and Walter Winchell attacks (official letter to Neue Volkszeitung, N.Y., 1945) (Box-folder 7: 2)
    - More slanderous accusations (Ruth Fischer and The Network) (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - Hagen defenders (statements, letters), 1937, 1940-1941, 1961 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    - Investigation of Paul Hagen, 1940 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - Ruth Fischer and The Network (Box-folder 7: 6)
    - A plan to make contact with the German underground movement (Lt. Col. Julius Klein), 1942 (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - Knox College, Galesburg, Ill. (two courses taught by Frank), 1945 (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Applications for a teaching position in social psychology, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 7: 9)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1939-1958
  Includes correspondence with Fritz Erler, Willy Brandt, Carl Zuckmayer, Thomas Mann, Dr. Hans E. Hirschfeld, Laumann, Gerth, Grzesinski, Gurland, Ruth Fischer, and others (see appended list of correspondents).
  - A - L (Box-folder 8: 1-11)
  - M - Z (Box-folder 9: 1-12)
  - Unidentified correspondence (Box-folder 9: 13)
  - Originals which have been xeroxed (Box 10)
  - List of correspondents
    - Adamec, Charles J. (Dean of Knox College)
    - Adelphi College (New York)
    - Adler, Friederich (letters to Dr. Mara Loewenstein and Dr. Wilhelm Ellenbogen)
    - Almond, Gabriel (Brooklyn College, Brooklyn, New York)
    - American Association for International Law (New York)
    - American College Bureau (Chicago, Illinois)
    - American Friends Service Committee Program in Austria
    - American Platform Guild (New York)
    - American Political Science Association
    - Das Andere Deutschland; Der Beauftragte in Süudhilfe (Osorno, Chile)
    - Anderson, Mrs. Evelyn (The Tribune, London)
    - Anglemeyer, Mary (Post Librarian, New York)
    - D. Appleton-Century Company, Inc. (London)
    - Arnhold, Erna
    - Ascoli, Max
    - Asher, Robert
    - Auerbach, Carl (Office of Economic Stabilization)
    - Baerensprung, H. W.
    - Baldwin, Roger (American Civil Liberties Union)
    - Bauer, Fritz
    - Beaty, Lt. Col. John O.
    - The Bell Syndicate, Inc. (New York)
    - Bernenko, Herbert (Men's Club of the Church in the Gardens, New York)
    - Biemiller, Andrew J. (Congress of the United States, House of Representatives, Washington, D.C.)
    - Binder, Carroll (Foreign Editor of The Chicago Daily News)
    - Bingham, Alfred M.
    - Blankinship, Rex, M.D. (letter to Mrs. M.W. Barrett, Norfolk, Virginia re Mrs. Frank)
    - Blatt, Max
    - Blencke, E. Elizabeth
    - Bliven, Bruce (The New Republic)
    - Blumenthal, H. Walter (Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, Washington, D.C.)
    - Boeker, Alexander (Human Events)
    - Boenheim, Felix, M.D. (letter to Mr. Tillich)
    - Books, New York Herald Tribune
    - Borgess, Elizabeth Mann (University of Chicago)
    - Brandstrom-Ulic, Elsa
    - Brandt, Karl (Economist, Food Research Institute, Stanford University)
    - Brandt, Willy (Mayor of Berlin)
    - Braun, Hans
    - Brill, Major
    - Brody, Sylvia
    - Brunauer, Mrs. Esther Caukin
    - Brunner, Robert (Psychiatric Books, New York)
    - Bry, Gerhard
    - Burger, Mrs. Richard (Dorothy S.)
    - Buttinger, Joseph
    - Cantril, Hadley (Princeton University)
    - Carter, Edward C.
    - Churchill, Frank Spooner, M.D.
    - The Church-in-the-Gardens, New York
    - Cohen, Carl
    - Cohen, Felix
    - Colclough, Elizabeth
    - Colgate University (signed Charles A. Choquette)
    - The Cooperative League of the United States of America, New York
    - Coser, Lewis A.
    - Cowling, Elizabeth
    - Cripps, Lady
    - Currie, Lauchlin (The White House, Washington, D.C.)
    - DAD Tucuman (Buenes Aires)
      Includes letter from Bruno Suess.
    - Davis, Elmer (Office of War Information)
    - Davis, Mrs. Rodney
    - Denison, W. H.
    - Denny, George V., Jr.
    - Department of Justice
    - Department of State, press release
    - Deutsch, Hermann
    - Donaldson, Henry H.
    - Dorn, Walter M.
    - Dorner, Lydia
    - Downing, George E.
    - Doyle, James
    - Drechsler, Hanno (Institut fuer wissenschaftliche Politik, Marburg a.L., Germany)
    - Drob, Judah (Socialist Party of Michigan)
    - Dufty, Bill (Americans for Democratic Action)
    - Duncker, Hermann
    - Eckardt, H. von
    - Eckardt, Ursula von (Foreign Policy Association, Speakers Bureau)
    - Edinger, Lewis J.
    - Ehrmann, Henry W.
    - Eisler-Pleuchot, Elfriede
    - Elder, Arthur A. (Workers Educational Service, University of Michigan)
    - Eliasberg, George (and Vera)
    - Emerson, William
    - Enderle, August
    - Erler, Fritz
    - Farrar and Rinehart (Publishers, New York)
    - Farren, Harry D. ("Wake Up, America!" Debate-in-Print; American Economic Foundation, New York)
    - Feakins, William B.
    - Ferber, Martin
    - Filley, Walter, Jr.
    - Fischer, George
    - Fischer, Louis
    - Fischer, Ruth and Adolf Weingarten (The Network, New York)
    - Fowler, Henry H. (Foreign Economic Administration)
    - Fox, Dixon Ryan (New York State Citizens Council for a Durable Peace)
    - Fox, Mary (League for Industrial Democracy, New York)
    - France, Ethel
    - France, Prof. Royal W. (Rollins College)
    - Frank, Hans (Karl Frank's brother)
    - Frank, Mrs. Karl (letters signed "Bi")
    - Frank, Peter (Karl Frank's nephew)
    - Franke, Vera
    - Frankel, Mrs. Hilde
    - Fredrikson, Mrs. Hildegard
    - Freedland, Jean
    - Freedman, Abraham L.
    - Free World
    - Friedman, Samuel H. (The Call)
    - Fry, Varian (American Labor Conference on International Affairs, New York)
    - Gardiner, Arthur Z.
    - Gattis, C. H. (Seaboard Air Line Railroad Co.)
    - Gauss, Christian (Princeton University)
    - Gerth, H. H. (University of Wisconsin)
    - Gezork, Herbert (letter to Miss Hartog)
    - Giddens, Josephine
    - Ginsburg, David
    - Godell, Mrs. Charles (American College Bureau, Chicago)
    - Gold, Mary Jayne
    - Goldbloom, Maurice J.
    - Gordon, J. King (The Nation)
    - Graham, Bess F. (Young Women's Christian Association, Alton, Illinois)
    - Greyl, Eva Toni
    - Gross, Murray
    - Grossman, Kurt R. (letter to Heinrich Dietz)
    - Grzesinski, Albert C.
    - Guggenheim, John Simon (Memorial Foundation, New York)
    - Guttentag, Werner
    - Hafkerbrick, Hanna (Connecticut College)
    - Haldemann (Julius) Publications
    - Hall, Helen
    - Hanna, Prof. John
    - Hannemann, Maria
    - Harvard University
    - Hasche, Paul
    - Haskell, Gen. William N. (Cooperative for American Remittances to Europe, Inc., New York)
    - Heckert, Robert
    - Heermance, Edgar L.
    - Hellersberg, Dr. Elisabeth F.
    - Herling, John
    - Herling, Mary Fox
    - Hermens, Ferdinand A.
    - Hertz, Dr. Paul (Berlin, Germany) (Senator)
    - Hillebrand, Eric A. (German American Congress for Democracy)
    - Hiller, Kurt
    - Hirsch, Helmut (Roosevelt College of Chicago)
    - Hirsch, Paul
    - Hirschfeld, Dr. Hans E.
    - Hochman, Julius
    - Hoeber, Johannes U.
    - Hoerlin
    - Holbrook, Sabra
    - Hollander, Sidney
    - Honnold, William L.
    - Hovde, Bryn J.
    - Hraswith, Josef
    - Ingersoll, Julia D. (Rockford College, Illinois)
    - Isenberg, Gerda
    - Jeffrey, Newman
    - Johnson, Maj. Lent C.
    - Jones, Prof. Howard M.
    - Juchacz, Marie
    - Kaskel, Joseph (Deutsche Blätter, Santiago de Chile)
    - Kaskel, Lilo
    - Klatt, Werner
    - Klein, Ernest L.
    - Klein, Lt. Col. Julius
    - Kleinman, S., M.D.
    - Kliem, Kurt (Institut für wissenschaftliche Politik, Marburg a.L., Germany)
    - Knoeringen, Waldemar von
    - Kowler, S.
    - Krahn, Elmer A. (The New Milwaukee Leader)
    - Kramer, Ernst
    - Kraus, Dr. Wolfgang H.
    - Kuh, Edwin J., Jr.
    - LaFollette, Hon. Charles M. (Congressman) (letter to Reinhold Niebuhr)
    - Lafrentz, F. W. (American Surety Company, New York)
    - Lamm, Hans
    - Lampel, Mrs. Martin
    - Landau, Dr. Edmund
    - Lang, Erna and Joseph
    - Lange, Dr. Victor (Cornell University)
    - Laumann, Kurt
    - Lee, Dwight L. (Clark University, Massachusetts)
    - Lefebre, Marshall
    - Leighton, Joseph A.
    - Lengh, Dr. Franz
    - Lewinski, Eva (International Rescue and Relief Committee, New York)
    - Lewis, David (Co-operative Commonwealth Federation of Canada)
    - Littell, Normann M. (Department of Justice, Washington, D.C.
    - Lochner, Louis P.
    - Loeb, Ellen
    - Loeb, James Jr. (Union for Democratic Action, Washington, D.C.)
    - Lowenthal, Richard
    - Luft, Dr. Lothar
    - Luttermann, K.
    - International LYCEUM Association (Chicago, Illinois)
    - Maencken, Otto
    - Maley, Alexander B.
    - Mann, Thomas
    - Mark, Agathe
    - "Markoosha" (?)
    - Marseille, Walter W.
    - Mason, Edward S.
    - Matzenauer, Eva
    - Matzenauer, Friedrich
    - Matzenauer, Grete
    - Matzenauer, Lutz
    - Maurer, Erwin
    - "Maxwell" (?) (War Department, Office of the Under Secretary, Washington, D.C.)
    - May, Stacy (McGraw-Hill Publishing Co., Inc., New York)
    - Maynard, William Doby
    - McClurg, A.C., & Co. (Chicago, Illinois)
    - McClurg, Miss Peggy (Union for Democratic Action, Chicago, Illinois)
    - McCullogh, Frank (Union for Democratic Action, Chicago, Illinois)
    - McGohey, John F. X.
    - Mead, James M.
    - Mellen, Sydney L. W.
    - Mendelsohn-Kirchner, Eva
    - Mendershausen, Horst
    - Meyer, Hans B.
    - Meyer, Richard A.
    - Minkel, Lester M.
    - Modern Age Books, Inc., New York
    - Morrison, Edith G.
    - Morse (Inspector, U.S. Immigration and Naturalization Service, New York)
    - Motherwell, Mrs. Hiram
    - Muller, Henry E. (Unitarian Service Committee, New York)
    - National Educational Committee for a New Party (New York)
    - Nehring, A. (Fordham University)
    - Neuhaus, Dr. F. T.
    - New Europe (New York)
    - Niebuhr, Reinhold
    - Office for Emergency Management, Washington, D.C.
    - Ogar, Ted (United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America, Detroit, Michigan)
    - Ogden, Urban L. (The First Christian Church, Duncy, Illinois)
    - Oldenberg, Prof. O.
    - Ollendorf, E.
    - Ollendorf, Robert
    - Open Forum Speakers Bureau, Boston, Massachusetts
    - Ottman, W. P.
    - Pactel, Karl Otto
    - Paige, Maud
    - Peat (Harold R.) Inc. (New York)
    - Pepper, Lisl Kallberg
    - Perry, Bernard B. (Current Books, Inc., New York)
    - Phillips, William
    - Piper, Otto A. (Princeton Theological Seminary)
    - Pinchot, Cornelia Bryce
    - Pinchot, Gifford
    - PM Daily (New York)
    - Poole, DeWitt C.
    - Porter, Paul R.
    - Pratt, Eliot
    - Pratt, James
    - Pratt, Trude
    - Preisz, Hugo
    - Pringsheim, Karl
    - The Progressive (Madison, Wisconsin)
    - Pusch, Werner
    - "Raemaker" (?)
    - Randall, Mrs. Mercedes
    - Ranke, Hubert
    - Reich, Ilse Ollendorf
    - Reich, Wilhelm, M.D.
    - Reissig, Herman F. (First Union Congregational Church, Quincy, Illinois)
    - Reizenstein, Mrs. Florence S.
    - Resek, Judith (Queens College, New York)
    - Reuther, Victor G. (United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America)
    - Reventlow, R.
    - Reynolds, Alice H.
    - Riesenfeld, Dr. F. D.
    - Robert, Oscar
    - Roberts, Elizabeth
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor
    - Rosenbaum, Max (East Bronx Community Y.M.C.A. and Y.W.C.A., New York)
    - Rossi, Florence (International Solidarity Committee and Socialist Party, New York)
    - Rother, Bruno
    - Rother, Rudolf (Bergverlag Rudolf Rother, Munich, Germany)
    - Rothfels, Prof. Hans
    - The Royal Institute of International Affairs, London
    - Rutz, Henry (Office of War Information, Washington, D.C.)
    - Saint Clair, Mrs. Peyton (Michaela, Karl Frank's daughter)
    - Sarah Lawrence College (New York)
    - Save Europe Now Committee (South Bend, Indiana)
    - Scherber, Hans
    - Schmidt, Duscha
    - Schmidt, Erich
    - Schocken, Thomas D.
    - Schoettle, Erwin
    - Schonfeld, Otto P.
    - Schwarz, Dr. Paul
    - Schwarz, Dr. Rudi
    - Schweitzer, Arthur
    - Seidlin, Oskar
    - Selig, Anna M.
    - Shaw, David C.
    - Shuster, George N.
    - Simons, Hans (The New School, New York)
    - Sizes, Mrs. W.
    - Smith, Anthony W. (Congress of Industrial Organizations, Washington, D.C.)
    - Snevily, Henry M. (The Bell Syndicate, Inc., New York)
    - Snyder, George M.
    - Social-Democratic Federation of U.S.A. (New York)
    - Socialist Party (New York)
    - Sonnemann, Ulrich
    - Sprengel, Rita
    - State Department, Passport Division, Washington, D.C.
    - Stecher, Ada E.
    - Steen, Margaret H. (The Masters School, New York)
    - Stein, Alexander
    - Steinberg, Karin M.
    - Stevenson, Adlai E.
    - Stewart, William H. (Saint Mark's Methodist Church, New York)
    - Stinnes, Edmund H.
    - The Summer Institute for Social Progress at Wellesley, Massachusetts
    - Survey Associates, Inc., New York
    - Survery Graphic (New York)
    - Tanner, Mrs. Mary F.
    - Taurer, Bernhard
    - Taylor, Amos E. (Department of Commerce, Washington)
    - Thompson, Dorothy
    - Tillich, Prof. Paul (Council for a Democratic Germany, New York)
    - True, Mrs. George R.
    - Tschermerinsky-Maslow, A. (American Friends of German Freedom, New York)
    - Tumarin, Bertha
    - Ulich, Prof. Robert (Harvard University)
    - Victor, Walther
    - Viking Press
    - Villard, Oswald Garrison
    - Vischer, Wilhelmina
    - Voorhis, Jerry (U.S. Congressman)
    - Voss, Carl Hermann
    - "Wake Up, America!" Debate-in-Print, New York
    - Walker, Patrick Gordon
    - Walker, Stanley
    - Walser, Frank
    - Warburg, James P.
    - Wasjadnock, Mrs. Otto
    - Wechsler, James
    - Weil, Helen
    - Weiss, Dr. Franziska
    - Weiss, Hilda (Connecticut College)
    - Welsh, Dale D. (University of Dubuque, Iowa)
    - Westermeyer, Prof. H. E.
    - Wilhide, Dr. Ross (First Methodist Church, Kenton, Ohio)
    - Willard, Ernst
    - Willcox, Walter F.
    - Wille, Werner
    - Willen, Mrs. Joseph
    - Williams, Edward Y.
    - Williams, Dr. H. Franklin
    - Williams, Howard Y. (Union for Democratic Action, Chicago, Illinois)
    - Wolf, Herman
    - Wolff, Hugh W.
    - Woll, Matthew (American Association for a Democratic Germany, New York)
    - World Citizens Association (Chicago, Illinois)
    - Wrightson, Jim
    - Yost, Charles
    - Youthbuilders (New York)
    - Zoller, E.
    - Zuckmayer, Karl
    - Zuckmayer, Winnetou
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1946 (Photo file)
  10 prints / 1 envelope
  - 8 photographs of Karl Frank alone or with wife or friend; 1 portrait of Johann Lenk; 1 portrait of Robert Heckert (Envelope A)